Janu is not ready yet.
Janu masih belum siap.
So, we're going to wait.
Kita tunggu.
- Rana? - Janu!
- Rana? - Janu!
What are you doing?
Sedang apa kau?
Let's go! Come with me to the woods.
Ayo, antar aku ke hutan.
What are you gonna do in the woods?
Untuk apa ke hutan?
I want to make a gift for Mom's birthday.
Membuat hadiah untuk Ibu.
I told Dad I was going with you.
Aku sudah izin Bapak untuk pergi dengan Mas Janu.
What? But you didn't tell me.
Mengapa kau tidak memberitahuku?
Let's just go.
Ayo, cepat antar aku.
But are you sure told your dad?
Benarkah kau sudah izin Bapak?
I did. Now come on.
Sudah. Sudah, ayo cepat, Mas.
My goodness, Rana...
Aduh, Rana...
Okay, hang on a minute.
Tunggu sebentar, ya.
- Hurry up, okay? - Okay, okay.
- Jangan lama-lama ya, Mas. - Ya.
Ladies and gentlemen,
Bapak-Bapak, Ibu-Ibu, dan Saudara-Saudara,
we are deeply saddened to inform you
aku ingin menyampaikan berita duka.
that our daughter, Rana,
Anak kami, Rana,
has been lost in the woods since yesterday afternoon.
hilang di hutan sejak kemarin sore.
- Rana!
- Rana!
I would very much appreciate it if we went together
Aku minta tolong
to search for our daughter, Rana, in the woods.
mencari anak kami, Rana, di hutan.
Rana!
Rana!
Sister!
Mbak!
I hope she'll be found alive and unharmed.
Semoga Rana bisa ditemukan dalam keadaan selamat dan hidup.
Amen.
Amin.
I thank you
Atas keikhlasan
for all your sincere concern and help.
Bapak-Bapak, Ibu-Ibu, dan Saudara-Saudara,
I appreciate it very much.
aku mengucapkan terima kasih banyak.
- Here you go, sir. - Thank you.
- Terima kasih. - Pak, pamit dulu.
Yes.
Ya.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
- Hey. - Yes?
- Hei, Pak. - Ya?
Why do a Tahlil ritual if they haven't found the body?
Padahal jenazahnya belum ditemukan, tapi mengapa sudah tahlilan?
I'm not surprised.
Biasalah.
According to Miss Nur, after calculating her birth date, it is time. Right?
Menurut Mbak Nur, dari perhitungan weton, ya memang sudah waktunya. Ya, 'kan?
But she has only been gone for a week. Is it okay to do a Tahlil ritual?
Padahal baru tujuh hari hilang, tapi sudah tahlilan ya?
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Are you sure? Do you really have to go?
Sungguh, Mbak? Yakin mau berangkat?
Stop asking me questions.
Mengapa Ibu terus bertanya?
You expect a mother not to ask questions of her own daughter?
Mbak, masa Ibu tidak bertanya?
- Mom, I have to do something very urgent. - How urgent can it be?
Ibu, Rana harus membuat sesuatu yang sangat amat penting.
- Very urgent. - Can you do it another day?
- Sangat amat penting, Ibu. - Mengapa seperti tidak ada hari lain?
What about my birthday?
Ulang tahun Ibu bagaimana?
Mom, before you blow the candles, I promise I'll be back home, okay?
Ibu, sebelum Ibu tiup lilin, Rana sudah di rumah, oke?
- Are you sure? - Absolutely.
- Sungguh? - Ya.
- You'll bring some snacks? - Yes.
- Sudah bawa makanan kecil? - Sudah.
- Water? - I will. Okay?
- Minum? - Sudah. Ya?
Bye.
Dah.
- That kiss is new. - Let's do arm-wrestling then.
- Tumben romantis. - Ya sudah, kita panco.
No, that's a boy's game.
Jangan. Seram seperti laki-laki.
- Bye, Mom. - Bye, sweetheart.
- Dah, Ibu. - Dah, Mbak.
- Be careful out there. - Okay, bye!
- Hati-hati ya. - Baiklah. Dah.
You've cleaned everything?
Sudah selesai?
Everything?
Sudah semua?
Sis.
Mbak.
This is the Yasin from Mom's funeral.
Ini Yasin Ibu waktu meninggal.
All right, I'll tell Sis Nur.
Ya, nanti aku bilang Mbak Nur.
- Sis Nur... - It was made long ago.
- Mbak Nur... - Itu buatnya sudah lama.
If I'm not mistaken, it was...
Waktu itu kalau tidak salah...
Fitting into this big family is not easy, Din.
Memahami keluarga besar memang tidak mudah, Din.
As a Javanese man myself, I find it hard too.
Aku saja yang orang Jawa terasa sulit.
I can understand since you're not even Javanese.
Apalagi kau yang bukan orang Jawa.
- Too much work. - I didn't tell them anything.
- Repot. - Aku tidak cerita apa-apa.
- Just hang in there. - But I want something like Mom's Yasin.
- Sabar ya. - Modelnya persis seperti Yasinnya Ibu.
- Thank you. - Well?
- Terima kasih, Mas. - Jadi?
It's okay.
Ya, tidak apa-apa.
But we have to agree on something first.
Yang penting kita sepakat dulu.
What date do you want to be put in the obituary?
Ini tanggal kematiannya mau ditulis kapan?
I didn't think of that.
Benar juga.
Well, what date?
Jadi, bagaimana?
Do you want the date of her disappearance
Ini mau dianggap pas hari hilangnya,
or the date they called off the search?
atau setelah pencariannya ditutup, Mbak?
Not the date of her disappearance.
Jangan hari hilangnya.
That's a cursed day.
Itu hari sial.
"Monday Pon.
"Hari Senin Pon
The day of the dead,
adalah hari menuju kematian
and a cursed day.
dan hari nahas.
Meaning, a terrible fate will be upon the person,
Artinya, kemalangan bagi manusia dan berkalang tanah.
In other words, they will be swallowed by the earth.
Dapat diartikan juga terpendam dalam Bumi.
But it is the person's fate.
Memang waktu itu sudah saatnya.
It will be their last day on Earth.
Waktu akhir kehidupan di muka Bumi."
It means
Artinya,
death.
mati.
Then, we're not gonna use that date.
Ya kalau begitu, jangan.
I don't want more bad luck on her 40th-day memorial ceremony.
Nanti 40 harinya kena masalah lagi.
All right, then.
Ya sudah.
Let's agree on the date.
Kalau begitu, kita sepakati saja ya.
Let's agree it's the date when they called off her search.
Kita taruh tanggalnya setelah pencarian ditutup.
Is that okay?
Setuju?
Look at how easily you are talking about death.
Mudah sekali untuk kalian membicarakan kematian.
You seem to love controlling someone's life and death.
Dari dulu kalian selalu mengarahkan kapan hidup dan matinya seseorang.
But you know the truth.
Padahal kalian semua juga tahu.
Her body hasn't been discovered yet.
Ini jenazahnya belum ketemu.
Din.
Din...
I want you to be strong.
Coba yang sabar.
There's nothing we can do when it comes to someone's fate.
Kalau memang sudah waktunya, sudah takdirnya, mau bagaimana lagi?
You want me to believe in fate? Fate according to whom?
takdir menurut siapa yang harus aku percayai?
We just want the deceased to rest in peace.
Kita di sini cuma mau yang terbaik untuk Mendiang.
That's why we have to pick the date.
Itu sebabnya harus cepat dipilih tanggal baiknya.
Her name is Rana.
Rana namanya.
Not "the deceased."
Bukan "Mendiang".
I am her mother.
Aku ibunya.
I know what's best for my daughter.
Aku tahu apa yang terbaik untuk anakku.
And what are you doing now?
Yang kalian lakukan ini apa?
You invited people for a Tahlil ritual. You decided the date of her death.
Mengadakan tahlilan, menentukan tanggal kematian,
You gave up. Do you think giving up is better?
menyerah...
How do you know which is better?
Kau tahu dari mana yang lebih baik?
I warned you
Sudah aku peringatkan.
that if you let Rana go that day, misfortune would happen.
Kalau Rana pergi hari itu, dia akan celaka, tapi kau membiarkan.
You're still resisting our beliefs.
Kau tidak pernah mau percaya omongan keluarga kami.
Even though you knew this wasn't the first time.
Padahal kau juga tahu
Now, your foolishness has claimed your daughter,
Sekarang anakmu celaka,
and you still refuse to believe?
tapi masih tidak percaya juga?
I will believe
Aku hanya ingin percaya
only if my daughter comes back alive.
kalau anakku masih hidup.
Is that so wrong?
Apa itu salah?
Rana?
Rana?
Rana...
Rana...
Rana!
Rana!
Sri.
Sri, bicaralah kepada Banyu.
Why me? Why don't you tell him?
Mengapa aku? Mbak saja yang bicara.
You're closer to him.
Kau yang lebih dekat dengannya.
How about we let Sis Nur tell him?
Atau Mbak Nur saja yang bicara sama Banyu.
You're right. She knows how to calculate properly according to the book.
Itu memang yang paling benar. Mbak Nur yang tahu perhitungannya.
- But we have to do it now, or... - Sis!
- Tapi segera, takutnya... - Mbak!
What are you discussing?
Sedang bicarakan apa?
How's Rana? What did she tell you?
Bagaimana keadaan Rana?
Did she get hurt?
Apa dia terluka?
Your niece has returned.
Keponakanmu sudah pulang, Mbak.
Stop thinking about bad stuff.
Mengapa berpikir seperti itu?
Banyu, if she was still alive, why did she only come home after seven days?
Banyu, kalau dia memang bertahan, mengapa baru hari ketujuh dia pulang?
I don't know.
Aku tidak mengerti, Mbak.
But she looks fine to me.
Rana terlihat sehat.
Use your brain.
- Apa kalian bisa berpikir? - Hei, tapi apa ada yang aneh?
Are her feet touching the ground?
Apa kakinya menapak?
Why don't you check on your daughter?
Coba periksakan anakmu.
I can't believe you. How could you?
Pikiranmu itu, Mbak... Pikiranmu.
- Can you believe them? - Calm down, Banyu.
- Mas, bagaimana ini? - Sabar, Banyu.
I can't believe how badly age is damaging your minds.
Mengapa kedua kakakku makin tua makin tidak bisa berpikir?
- Why are you mad at us? - My calculation is accurate.
- Mengapa kau menjadi marah? - Hitungannya tidak mungkin salah.
She's right. You should listen to your older sister.
Dengarkan mbakmu. Dia sudah benar.
I need your support.
Aku membutuhkan dukungan.
She was lost and now she has been found. Stop complicating the situation.
Hilang, pulang, malah direcoki begini, jadinya bagaimana?
What song is this?
Lagu apa ini?
You missed us, didn't you?
Rindu ya, Mbak?
Everybody said
Semua orang bilang
that you were gone.
katanya kau sudah pergi.
"You have to be strong."
Ibu harus kuat dan ikhlas.
But, Rana, I knew. I believed.
Tapi, Rana, Ibu tahu dan yakin...
I knew you were still alive.
Mbak masih hidup.
You promised, didn't you?
Kau sudah berjanji. Ya, 'kan?
You promised to come home.
Janji mau pulang, 'kan?
That you'd come home. Right?
Ternyata kau sungguh pulang.
Forgive me, Mom.
Maaf ya, Bu.
What for?
Mengapa minta maaf?
Never apologize.
Tidak boleh minta maaf.
You're home, sweetheart.
Kau sudah pulang, Mbak.
You're home.
Kau pulang, Mbak.
Tari.
Dek,
Has your sister taken a shower?
Mbak sudah mandi?
She just went into the bathroom.
Baru masuk.
Here, do me a favor.
Ini, tolong. Handuknya simpan di kamar mandi.
Okay.
Ya.
Tari.
Tari,
Your prayers have been answered.
doamu juga terkabul.
I want you to help me and your father. Let's keep your sister safe.
Bantu Ibu dan Bapak, ya? Kita jaga Mbak bersama.
Okay?
Bantu, ya?
Sis?
Mbak?
You're done showering?
Mandinya sudah, Mbak?
It's not funny, you know.
Mbak, tidak lucu.
I thought I had some noodles left yesterday.
Minya masih ada kemarin.
I think it's been a while since the last time we bought instant ramen.
Mas, sepertinya sudah lama tidak membeli mi instan, ya?
Can you buy them for me?
Nanti beli, ya.
Just in case Rana needs a midnight snack and finds nothing in the drawer.
Mbak takutnya terbangun tengah malam, lalu kelaparan, dan tidak ada makanan.
I think I'd better call a doctor, Din.
Aku ingin memanggil dokter, Din.
I don't think we need a doctor.
Sepertinya tidak perlu, Mas.
I've checked her. No cuts or bruises.
Tadi aku sudah memeriksa semuanya, tidak ada luka.
But Nur said we should be cautious.
Mbak Nur bilang kita harus hati-hati.
Making sure is not a bad thing, right?
Tidak ada salahnya, 'kan?
Just in case. If anything happened to her, we'd be prepared.
Kita berjaga-jaga.
Are you afraid of your own daughter?
Apa kau takut dengan anakmu sendiri?
That's not what I meant.
Bukannya takut.
I said, if anything happened to her, we'd be prepared.
Aku bilang, jika ada yang tidak beres, kita sudah siap.
Prepared for what?
Siap-siap apa?
I can't believe this.
Heran, mengapa kau bisa seperti ini?
How could a father not seem happy to see his dead daughter come home alive?
Ada seorang ayah yang tidak senang
How odd.
Aneh.
You should be happy.
Seharusnya kau senang, Mas.
Everybody saw her. She's here in the flesh.
Kita semua melihatnya, ada bentuknya.
Your daughter...
Anakmu itu benar-benar baru pulang
- Don't say that. - Well?
- Jangan bicara begitu. - Lantas?
I'm just saying.
Aku hanya bilang.
It's better to be safe than sorry.
Lebih baik kita tahu, untuk siap-siap.
Honey, that's it. I'm sick and tired of this nonsense.
Mas, sudah ya. Aku lelah.
I know your sisters have poisoned your mind.
Ini pasti karena mbak-mbakmu.
Their blind belief in the Primbon book is driving them crazy.
Gara-gara kepercayaan mereka terhadap primbon yang berlebihan,
I'm sorry. But I just want to share my thoughts.
Maafkan aku. Aku hanya ingin menyampaikan.
The more we know, the better, Din.
Kalau kita bisa tahu lebih banyak, artinya itu lebih bagus, Din.
I know, but not...
Ya, tapi bukan...
- But... - Enough.
- Sudah. - Berhenti...
Let's drop this topic, okay?
Sudah, tidak perlu dibahas lagi.
Don't cry.
- Jangan menangis. - Sudah, tidak.
After you went missing, Mom and Dad wouldn't stop fighting.
Bapak dan Ibu memang suka berdebat seperti itu selama Mbak hilang.
I began to get used to it.
Tidak apa-apa, sudah biasa.
I know they both missed you.
Mereka berdua merindukan Mbak.
Especially Mom.
Terutama Ibu, Mbak.
She didn't stop crying from the day you went missing.
Selama Mbak hilang, Ibu terus menangis.
She wouldn't cut her birthday cake until she knew you'd come home safe.
Ibu sampai tidak mau potong kuenya sebelum Mbak pulang.
What about your present?
Kadonya bagaimana, Mbak?
Did you make it?
Apa sudah jadi?
You're still tired?
Mbak masih lelah, ya?
We didn't know what to do when you went missing.
Waktu itu kita semua bingung harus melakukan apa, Mbak.
But Mom insisted that you were still alive.
Ibu sangat percaya bahwa Mbak masih hidup.
There were moments I doubted that you were.
Tari sempat tidak percaya kalau Mbak masih hidup.
I'm sorry for thinking about it.
Maafkan Tari ya, Mbak.
But I'm happy you're home now.
Tari senang Mbak pulang.
I missed you, sis.
Tari rindu, Mbak.
You just want to sing with Dad, huh?
Mbak hanya mau bertanya sama Bapak ya?
You want to sing with me.
Tidak mau sama Tari?
You're hungry, Na?
Lapar, Na?
Mom said they just released a new flavor.
Kata Ibu, ada rasa baru itu.
Your favorite brand.
Mi instanmu.
Let me get it for you at the market, okay?
Nanti Bapak coba cari di pasar.
Are you feeling okay?
Badanmu tidak apa-apa, 'kan?
I've asked Dr. Adi to come to examine you.
Bapak minta dokter Adi untuk memeriksamu.
It's only morning and I'm already in debt again.
Masih pagi sudah berutang.
- You're in debt again? - Yes.
- Kau berutang lagi? - Ya.
- Morning, ma'am. - Are you all ready?
- Bu. - Sudah makan sarapan?
Not yet, ma'am.
Belum, Bu.
- Excuse me, ma'am. - Yes.
- Permisi, Bu. - Ya.
Excuse me, ma'am.
- Permisi, Mbak. Mas.
- Hello, hello. - Yes.
- Permisi. - Ya, Mas.
Dad!
Pak!
Daddy!
Bapak!
What is it, sweetheart?
Ada apa, Mbak?
Ow.
Aduh.
Please, can I?
Boleh ya, Pak?
Na, it's dangerous. It's raining season now.
Na, sekarang itu bahaya. Musim hujan.
- You should avoid going to the woods. - But Janu will be there with me.
- Sebaiknya jangan ke hutan dulu. - Aku pergi bersama Janu.
Your aunt said you should stay home.
Bude Sepuh sudah bilang, kau jangan ke mana-mana dulu.
It's your mother's birthday too.
Lagi pula, hari ini juga ulang tahun Ibu.
Dad, I'll go with Janu.
Pak, aku pergi bersama Janu.
He can protect me.
Janu pasti menjaga Rana.
Okay? If anything happens, you should hold him responsible.
Ya? Nanti kalau ada apa-apa, Bapak tinggal salahkan Janu saja.
God forbid.
Jangan sampai ada apa-apa.
Just do as I say this time.
Sudahlah, menurut saja.
Or how about this?
Atau begini saja, Pak.
How about,
Bagaimana kalau setiap hari selama satu minggu,
Please?
Ya?
- Promise? - I promise.
- Benarkah? - Benar.
- Are you sure? - Yeah!
- Sungguh? - Ya.
- Again, promise? - I promise.
- Janji, ya? - Janji.
- I can't believe it. - Can I go now?
- Boleh. - Boleh?
Fine.
- Ya sudah. - Hore!
Be careful with the cleaver, Banyu.
Hati-hati, Banyu.
You'll cut your thumb instead of the fish.
Nanti bukannya ikan, malah jempolmu yang putus.
That's impossible.
Tidak, Mas.
Rana's not coming with you? She's already started taking classes?
Rana tidak ikut?
She's better staying at home still.
Lebih bagus dia di rumah, Mas.
The timing is not right.
Situasinya sedang seperti ini.
How is she anyway?
Bagaimana keadaan Rana?
She's okay, right?
Dia baik-baik saja, 'kan?
No bruises or injuries?
Tidak ada luka atau cedera, 'kan?
Her body is fine.
Kalau badan tidak ada luka, Mas.
But I can't say the same with her mind.
Tapi sepertinya di dalam dirinya yang terluka.
There you go.
Itu dia.
You know what?
Itu karena
That's because your big family is freaking out thinking she's a ghost.
baru datang langsung disangka setan oleh keluarga besarmu.
No wonder it's affecting her mind.
Pantas kalau lukanya di dalam.
- Sir. - Yes?
- Pak, beli cumi-cuminya. - Ya?
- Here you go. Thank you. - Thank you, sir.
- Ini, terima kasih. - Terima kasih, Pak.
Relax, Banyu.
Sudahlah, Banyu.
Stop overthinking it.
Tidak perlu terlalu didengarkan.
You know how your sisters are always exaggerating.
Mbak-mbakmu itu terkadang suka berlebihan.
They're treating the Primbon book as a life manual.
Memang primbon menjadi pegangan mereka sehari-hari.
When your mother was still with us,
Dulu waktu ibumu masih hidup,
I was like you.
aku juga begitu.
Catching fish had to wait until they approved the date.
Mau pergi melaut pun harus menunggu keputusannya.
"Is it a good day or a bad day to catch fish?" So complicated.
Harinya baik atau tidak. Repot, 'kan?
I was exactly like you.
Ya, aku juga seperti itu, Mas.
They were so furious when I told them I was going to marry Dini.
Waktu aku mau nikah dulu itu pada ribut semua.
Then my mother died.
Karena kejadian itu, Ibu meninggal.
Yes.
Ya.
But not everything is about their belief.
Tidak semua menyangkut kepercayaan mereka.
Blessed day or cursed day, who's to say?
Soal hari baik atau tidak, siapa yang tahu?
Right?
Benar, 'kan?
You're correct.
Ya, Mas.
Take Rana here tomorrow.
Besok Rana diajak ke sini.
What for?
Untuk apa?
Who knows?
Siapa tahu setelah makan ikan ini menjadi manusia.
What kind of human?
Manusia apa?
A human fish.
Ya manusia ikan.
That would be very scary.
Menyeramkan, Mas.
I know.
Ya.
Janu!
Mas Janu!
Janu...
Mas Janu...
Do you know Rana has returned home?
Mas Janu sudah tahu kalau Mbak Rana sudah pulang?
Don't you want to see her?
Mas tidak menjenguk?
It can't be.
Tidak mungkin.
Janu.
Mas.
- Here's 20 for the change, ma'am. - Yes.
- Kembali dua puluh ya, Bu. - Ya.
- Here you go. - Thank you, ma'am.
- Silakan. - Ya, terima kasih, Bu. Mari.
Ma'am.
- Bu... - Wah.
So this is why.
Pantas.
I wondered why my ears were twitching.
Kupingku dari tadi terus berkedut.
Apparently, I was getting a visit from an old customer.
Ternyata ada tamu yang sudah lama tidak datang.
- Your daughter has returned? - Yes, ma'am.
- Anakmu pulang, ya? - Ya, Bu.
That's why I came here.
Karena itu aku belanja sekarang, mau memasak makanan istimewa.
Which rice tastes better?
Mana beras yang lebih bagus?
- Is this the one? - I mean...
- Apa ini, ya? - Itu...
She returned on the night you held a Tahlil ritual?
Dia datang saat tahlilan, ya?
I wonder why?
Mengapa datang saat tahlilan?
Are you sure it's her?
Apa dia sungguh anakmu?
Be careful of haunting spirits.
Hati-hati, arwah gentayangan.
I'm not joking, ladies!
Ya, 'kan?
They're spirits who stay near their houses for the first 40 days after their death.
Arwah, selama 40 hari,
Mrs. Dini.
- Mbak Dini. - Ya?
What dream did you have before your daughter returned?
Mimpi apa anaknya kembali?
No dream at all. I don't trust dreams in this day and age.
Tidak ada mimpi, Bu. Zaman sekarang sudah tidak percaya mimpi.
But
Tapi
dreams can sometimes also come true.
mimpi itu juga sering ada yang menjadi kenyataan.
My neighbor once put down a pan, but it fell down and broke.
Tetanggaku meletakkan wajan, lalu jatuh kencang.
Not long after that, her neighbor died.
Tidak lama kemudian, dia meninggal.
- Are you sure? - I swear.
- Benar, Bu? - Benar.
Hey. Did you check with Miss Nur first?
Hei, sudah tanya Mbak Nur?
Was the premonition good or bad?
Firasat ini buruk atau bagus?
See?
Lihat, 'kan?
According to Primbon, when something falls,
Menurut primbon, kalau ada barang jatuh itu,
that means a relative is going to die.
tandanya akan ada anggota keluarga yang meninggal.
But you were talking about dreams. But this is not a dream at all.
Bu, itu kalau mimpi, 'kan? Ini tidak sedang bermimpi.
We all saw the pan fall.
Kita lihat sendiri wajannya jatuh.
Let me buy the pan, then. How much?
Sekalian saja aku beli wajannya. Berapa itu, Bu?
- You want to buy me a new one? - How much do you want for that?
- Mau diganti? - Berapa harganya?
Thank you, Din.
Terima kasih ya, Din.
Let's say you didn't dream about it at all.
Kalau bukan karena mimpi,
But did you get any premonition at all?
apa Mbak Dini tidak punya firasat?
Are you sure she's really your daughter?
Tidak takut? Itu benar anaknya Mbak Dini, bukan?
Ma'am, I've changed my mind about buying your rice.
Bu, aku tidak jadi beli berasnya.
What's going on?
Ada apa ini, Bu?
I can hear your yelling from my stall over there.
Ribut-ribut sampai terdengar dari sana.
If you want to meet Rana, you can come with me.
Kalau mau ketemu Rana, ayo.
You can see her for yourself. There's nothing wrong with her at all.
Biar lihat sendiri, tidak ada apa-apa.
Right?
Benar, 'kan?
Honey, please help.
Mas, ini.
- Have you paid for your groceries? - You can pay for the pan.
- Sudah dibayar belanjaannya? - Bayar dulu wajannya.
Regarding the pan, she said she was buying my pan.
Sama wajannya sekalian, katanya mau dibayarkan.
Yes, but not the rice. Just the pan.
Ya, berasnya tidak jadi beli, Bu. Wajannya saja.
Honey, just pay for the pan.
Mas, beli wajannya saja.
- How much? - It's up to you.
- Berapa? - Terserah, berapa saja.
You can't do that!
Mengapa terserah aku? Ini.
- Here you go. - Thank you.
- Sudah. - Terima kasih.
Sure.
- Ya. Permisi, Bu. - Ya.
- You're ready to go home? - Yes.
- Kau sudah mau pulang? - Sudah.
Can you buy some food on the way home?
Nanti beli makanan dulu, ya.
When I left the house, Rana was still sleeping.
Tadi saat aku pergi, Mbak masih tidur.
I don't want her to wake up hungry.
Kasihan kalau bangun, takutnya lapar.
I didn't want to wake her up.
Kasihan kalau dibangunkan.
She's alone at home?
- Rana sendirian di rumah? - Ya. Aku mau belanja dulu.
- Okay then, I'm leaving right now. - Okay.
- Jadi, aku langsung saja, ya? - Ya.
- Don't forget the lunch. - Are you okay being here alone?
- Cari makanan ya, Mas. - Kau tidak takut?
Sis.
Mbak, ini yang mau aku taruh di kamarnya Rana.
Is this much enough?
Sebanyak ini cukup?
It's for protection.
Buat pelindung.
If the flowers wilt immediately,
Nanti kalau membusuk,
then she's not human.
itu tandanya dia bukan manusia.
Aunt Ning.
Bude Ning.
I remember you used to love braiding my hair, right?
Dulu Bude Ning suka mengepang Rana, 'kan?
Aunt Nur told you many Primbon book stories, right?
Bude Ning banyak cerita-cerita primbon dari Bude Sepuh, 'kan?
Can you tell the stories again to me?
Apa Bude bisa menceritakannya lagi kepada Rana?
The Primbon Mangkuprajan book says this.
Kalau menurut primbon Mangkuprajan,
You were born on Saturday.
Rana itu lahir di hari Sabtu.
It is very influenced by earth.
Hari yang unsur tanahnya sangat kental.
That is why you are a special girl.
Itu sebabnya Rana menjadi anak yang istimewa.
You are loved by many...
Dan disukai banyak...
What's wrong, Aunt Ning?
Ada apa, Bude Ning?
Aunt Ning?
Bude Ning?
- What's wrong, sis? - Sri...
- Ada apa, Mbak? - Sri...
What happened?
Ada apa? Tadi bagaimana di rumah Rana?
I was braiding Rana's hair, Sri.
Tadi aku mengepang Rana, Sri.
But her scalp is rotting.
Tapi kulit kepalanya sudah busuk.
- There were maggots everywhere, Sri. - Oh my...
- Sampai keluar ulat-ulat, Sri. - Astaga.
I freaked out!
Aku jijik.
You're freaking me out.
Mengapa menyeramkan begitu, Mbak?
Sri...
Sri...
Don't you realize?
Apa kau sadar?
From the day she went missing,
Sejak Rana menghilang,
that plaintive cuckoo hasn't stopped singing in front of Banyu's house.
burung kedasih itu tidak berhenti berbunyi dari depan rumahnya Banyu.
You know what sign that is?
Kau tahu itu pertanda apa, 'kan?
That's the sign of kepaten, Sri.
Itu tandanya ada kepaten, Sri.
There's death in the house.
Ada yang mati di rumah itu.
You're right.
Benar juga, ya?
But if Rana were really dead,
Tapi kalau memang Rana mati,
how come we can still see her in the flesh?
mengapa wujudnya masih kita lihat, Mbak?
I don't know, Sri.
Aku tidak tahu, Sri.
We should listen to what Sis Nur says.
Kita menurut sama Mbak Nur saja daripada nanti aku salah.
Oh my... you're right.
Aduh. Benar juga, ya?
Oh, no.
Aduh.
Sri.
- Sri... - Wah...
What's going on in here?
Ada apa ini?
Do you think I'm a ghost too?
Aku dianggap hantu juga?
- What's wrong? - You're startling us.
- Ada apa? - Kau membuat kami berdebar kencang.
- Oh... - What is it?
- Hei. - Apa?
I just want to ask your opinion.
Tapi aku mau tahu pendapatmu.
Let me ask you something.
Coba, aku penasaran.
Aren't you curious about whether that girl is really Rana or not?
Apa kau curiga itu Rana atau bukan?
I think we still have to prove that it's really her.
Kalau menurutku, ini harus tetap dibuktikan.
We did that when Sis Ning put down a tray of offering flowers.
Buktinya, tadi Mbak Ning sudah taruh sesajen di kamarnya.
Right, sis?
Ya, 'kan, Mbak?
Do you have the courage to retrieve the tray?
Memangnya kau berani memeriksa sesajennya?
Pray to God, Ning.
Berdoalah, Ning.
Ask Him to protect you from Rana.
Roh-roh jahat dari Rana sedang beraksi.
Aunt Sri.
Bude Sri.
You're looking for this, right?
Bude Sri mencari ini, 'kan?
Sis. What is it?
Ada apa ini, Mbak?
Just return it to Aunt Ning.
Kembalikan saja ini ke Bude Ning.
Sis!
Mbak!
Your Aunt is going crazy.
Budemu itu tidak jelas.
Okay?
Ya?
That's Dad's favorite rice.
Itu nasi kesukaan Bapak.
The stir-fried tempeh is good.
Tempe oreknya enak.
The boiled egg is good.
Telur pindangnya enak.
The fried vermicelli is also good.
Bihunnya juga enak.
Don't you like the food?
Apa kau tidak suka?
I love it.
Suka.
Then start to eat.
Kalau begitu, makanlah.
Today, at the market,
Tadi,
Mom almost made a scene in Mrs. Anik's stall.
Ibu mau membuat keributan lagi di warung Bu Anik.
But it was with another buyer.
Tapi sama ibu-ibu lain.
So, your Mom said
Jadi, ibumu itu bilang
Mrs. Anik's goods were filthy, dirty, and smelled rotten.
kalau dagangannya Bu Anik itu jorok, kotor, bau, tidak sedap.
But the real reason she did that was to get a low price.
Padahal ujung-ujungnya ingin menawar.
Your mother is smart, just like you.
Ibumu pintar sepertimu.
Eat the egg, it's good.
Telurnya dimakan, enak itu.
Oh my...
Astaga.
Are you okay, baby?
Ada apa denganmu, Na?
I told you not to go anywhere just yet.
Makanya kau jangan ke mana-mana dulu.
You have to eat healthy food and have a lot of sleep,
Makan yang benar, istirahat yang benar.
considering what just happened to you.
Kau baru saja mengalami kejadian seperti itu.
A pretty girl isn't supposed to have a nosebleed. Wipe your nose.
Anak cantik mengapa seperti itu? Dilap itu.
Excuse me.
Permisi.
Dr. Adi.
Dokter Adi.
- Good afternoon. - Good afternoon, Doc.
- Selamat siang. - Selamat siang, Pak.
- Please, come in. - Thank you.
- Silakan, Pak. - Ya.
- She's in there. - May I?
- Sebelah sana. - Boleh?
Sure, go ahead.
Ya, silakan.
Na, this is Dr. Adi.
Na, ini dokter Adi.
- Is this the patient? - Yes.
- Ini yang sakit? - Ya.
It's okay.
Tidak apa-apa.
Let's do a little health check.
Kita periksa, ya?
You'll be okay.
Nanti juga sembuh.
Excuse me, ma'am.
Permisi, Bu.
Can you open your mouth?
Bisa buka mulutnya?
Look up at the roof, please.
Agak mendongak.
There's nothing wrong with her, right, Doc?
Tidak apa-apa, 'kan, Pak Dokter?
She's fine.
Tidak apa-apa.
Can I use the bathroom?
Aku boleh ke toilet?
Yeah, sure. It's in the back. Down the hall.
Ya, silakan. Di belakang. Lurus aja.
Sis, I don't want to come in.
Mbak, aku tidak mau masuk.
Banyu!
Banyu!
We need to talk.
Aku mau bicara.
Now what? If you don't believe it, just come inside.
Ada apa lagi, Mbak? Kalau tidak percaya, ada di dalam.
Let's hear what the doctor says, okay?
Nanti kita dengar apa kata dokter, ya?
Doc?
Dok...
- She's okay, right? - She's okay.
- Tidak apa-apa, 'kan? - Tidak apa-apa.
Doctor... Doc!
Pak Dokter... Pak!
Why are you all outside?
Mengapa ada di luar?
May I know what you're discussing?
Bicara apa, Mbak?
It's not just about Rana.
Ini bukan hanya soal Rana.
Rana has become a magnet for bad spirits, attracting them to this property.
Tapi Rana sudah menjadi sumber penarik roh jahat yang berbahaya ke tempat ini.
That's impossible.
- Tidak masuk akal bagiku. - Tidak masuk akal bagimu.
Because you refuse to believe.
Karena memang kau tidak mau percaya.
Sri and I were tormented by evil spirits last night.
Semalam, aku dan Sri sudah diganggu sama roh jahat itu.
This bowl full of wilted flowers is the proof.
Bunga busuk ini buktinya.
When Sri went away with the tray, the flowers were still fresh.
Saat Mbak Sri membawanya, bunga ini masih bagus.
What did you put in my house?
Kau simpan apa di rumahku, Mbak?
What did you put in there?
Simpan apa, Mbak?
Nyu.
Nyu.
You're going to be sorry.
Kalian akan menyesal.
What is she talking about?
Ada apa ini, Mbak?
How is she doing?
Di mana Rana?
The doctor said she was fine.
Kata Dokter baik-baik aja, Mas.
Sis. Sis.
Mbak...
What are things going to come to if we let this happen?
Kalau seperti ini terus, bagaimana ini, Mbak?
Strange things keep on happening around us.
Makin hari makin banyak kejadian-kejadian aneh.
I don't want what happened to Mother to happen again.
Takutnya nanti kejadiannya seperti Ibu dulu.
Knock on wood.
Aduh, jangan sampai begitu.
Sis.
Mbak.
All the signs are clear, right?
Ini pertandanya sudah jelas, 'kan, Mbak?
Hang on.
Tunggu dulu.
What did the doctor say?
Dokternya bilang apa?
If the doctor didn't say anything,
Kalau dokternya tidak bilang apa-apa,
why should we believe in signs and the Primbon book and not science?
mengapa kita percaya pertanda dan primbon daripada manusia.
I'm confused.
Bagaimana ini?
Bas!
Bas!
What?
Apa?
Did I say something wrong?
Ucapanku ini benar, 'kan?
Have you forgotten what happened to Bagas?
Kau lupa apa yang terjadi sama Bagas?
Bagas died because you chose science!
Dia tidak ada karena kau lebih percaya sama manusia!
- Sis, you've crossed the line! - Calm down.
- Mbak, kau sudah keterlaluan! - Sudah.
Take it back!
Tidak pantas bicara seperti itu!
- How dare you! - Calm down, Sri.
- Mbak tidak punya perasaan! - Sudah, Sri.
How could Ning say that to me?
Mengapa Mbak Ning tega bicara seperti itu, Mas?
How could she be that cold?
Mengapa dia tega?
It made me so furious when she talked like that about Bagas.
Aku tidak terima kalau dia bicara soal Bagas.
I know. Calm down, Sri.
Ya. Sabar, Sri... Sabar.
We've talked about this before.
Kita sudah bahas ini.
Whatever happened to us, we did the best we could, Sri.
Apa pun yang terjadi kepada kita, itu yang terbaik untuk kita, Sri.
Right?
Ya, 'kan?
Calm down.
Sabar...
I know how you feel, Sri.
Aku tahu perasaanmu, Sri.
When Rana returned home, I thought about Bagas.
Waktu Rana pulang saat itu, aku pikir Bagas yang pulang.
Calm down, Sri. Calm down.
Sabar, Sri. Sabar.
Can I go with you, Dad?
Ikut, ya, Pak.
Okay.
Ya sudah.
What do you want, ma'am? Prawns as usual?
Apa, Bu? Udang? Biasa?
Yes.
Ya.
What else, ma'am?
Apa lagi, Bu?
Hey.
Bu, itu setan atau bukan?
- Why is she...? - That's Rana.
- Hei, Bu, mengapa dia... - Itu Rana.
Is that Rana?
Rana, ya?
But the girl beside him...
Di sebelah sana juga ada.
Isn't that Rana?
- Itu Rana, 'kan? - Benar juga.
I'm not imagining this, right?
- Ini sungguhan, 'kan, Bu? - Apakah ini sungguhan?
- That's really her, right? - My skin's crawling.
- Itu benar, 'kan? - Membuat kita merinding.
She's here.
Dia ada di sini.
So, your aunts, especially Aunt Nur, always say
Jadi, bude-budemu itu, terutama Bude Sepuh,
that if we want to celebrate something
kalau kita merayakan sesuatu atau ada yang baru sembuh dari sakit,
we have to make ketupat.
harus bikin ketupat.
I'm following their belief.
Ini, Ibu mengikuti
I'm doing everything they taught me and told me to do.
apa yang selama ini mereka selalu ajari dan bilang.
They should've been happy to see you home, all healthy and safe.
Seharusnya mereka senang kalau kau sudah pulang, sehat, selamat.
You should deliver them to your aunts.
Sekalian nanti kau yang antarkan ke budemu.
Can you make ketupat? Here, let me show you.
Kau yang buat, ya? Ibu ajari.
It's easy.
Gampang, Mbak.
- Teach me how, Mom. - Wrap it around your hand three times.
- Bagaimana caranya, Bu? - Putar seperti ini tiga kali.
Three times.
Putarlah tiga kali.
You got a short leaf!
Mengapa pendek ya, Mbak?
Here, use this one.
Mbak, tukar yang ini.
Yes, wrap it three times...
Ya, putar tiga...
Janu...
Mas Janu.
Why did you avoid me yesterday?
Mengapa Mas Janu menghindar kemarin?
Rana has returned, and you still haven't come to see her.
Mbak Rana pulang, Mas juga belum jenguk.
Why?
Mengapa?
What is this?
Ini apa, Mas?
I can't go on living like this.
Aku tidak bisa terus hidup seperti ini.
I'm tired of being terrorized by Rana every day.
Aku lelah diteror Rana setiap hari.
It was my fault. I forced her to go uphill.
Ini memang salahku. Aku yang paksa dia ke atas.
But I didn't know it was her cursed day.
Tapi aku tidak tahu itu hari sialnya dia.
- Careful, Ran. - Okay.
- Hati-hati, Ran. - Ya.
Be careful, Ran!
Hati-hati, Ran!
Rana!
Rana!
What? Are you confused?
Ada apa? Kau bingung?
The girl in your house
Yang di rumahmu itu
is not Rana.
bukan Rana.
What do you mean, not Rana?
Bukan Rana bagaimana?
When a person gets lost in the woods,
Orang yang hilang di hutan
the chance of them being alive is ten percent.
kemungkinan ditemukan hanya sepuluh persen,
Especially when they've been gone for a week.
apalagi kalau sudah hilang selama tujuh hari.
The only way for us to find Rana...
Satu-satunya cara agar kita menemukan Rana...
She has to be cleansed.
Dia harus diruwat.
If you say the girl in my house is not Rana,
Kalau yang di rumah bukan Mbak Rana,
then who is she?
lalu siapa?
The birth dates don't match!
Ini tanggal lahirnya tidak cocok.
- This one... - Don't show it to her.
- Ini... - Jangan sampai ada yang tahu, ya.
What is it, Sri?
Ada apa, Sri?
I miss Bagas.
Aku merindukan Bagas, Mas.
Me too.
Aku juga.
It's getting dangerous.
Ini sudah berbahaya.
It's getting dangerous!
Ini sudah berbahaya!
What is it, sis?
Ada apa, Mbak?
All the evil spirits... they're coming!
Makin banyak roh!
We should do a cleansing ritual for Rana.
Rana harus diruwat.
A cleansing ritual?
Diruwat?
It's okay.
- Tidak apa-apa. - Tidak usah, Mas.
This is for Aunt Nur and all of you.
Untuk Bude Sepuh dan yang lain.
Rana.
Rana,
If we hold a cleansing ceremony for you, is that okay with you?
kalau kau diruwat, tidak apa-apa, 'kan?
According to the Primbon book,
Menurut primbon,
after someone has been cleansed, they will become pure again.
setelah diruwat, bersih,
Then do it.
selesai, 'kan?
I just don't understand.
Mengapa
Why can't you all
kalian semua
believe my mother?
tidak percaya kepada Ibu?
I should leave now.
Rana pamit dulu.
I hope you like the ketupat.
Semoga suka ketupatnya.
We should not be afraid of Rana.
Kita tidak boleh takut dengan Rana.
We have to make Dini agree to hold a cleansing ceremony.
Kita harus memaksa Dini untuk mengadakan ruwatan.
We should hold a cleansing ceremony.
Rana harus diruwat.
You're living rent-free in this house.
Kau menumpang di sini.
I've made up my mind.
Ini tidak bisa diganggu gugat lagi.
I know I live rent-free here.
Memang aku menumpang di sini.
I have never been accepted by the family either.
Selama ini juga tidak pernah dianggap sebagai keluarga.
Because you refuse to become a part of this family.
Kau juga tidak pernah mau menjadi bagian dari keluarga kami.
You should've never got married.
Seharusnya kalian tidak menikah.
Your birth dates are not a match. That's bad luck.
Weton yang tidak cocok
And you were born on the wrong date.
Dan kau lahir di hari yang salah.
A cursed one.
Di hari yang sial.
And it is confirmed that you've brought a curse upon our family.
Dan sudah terbukti
Sister.
Mbak...
Now what?
Ada apa lagi ini, Mbak?
After you two got married, our mother passed away.
Sejak kalian menikah,
Now, you've lost your daughter. You have to realize it.
Sekarang anakmu hilang. Sadari itu.
You don't like me having come home either?
Kau juga tidak suka Mbak pulang?
About that, I know it all too well.
Kalau soal itu, aku sadar betul.
From the moment I entered this house,
Dari dulu, di rumah ini,
this family,
di keluarga ini,
I've been judged to be the bearer of misfortune. A magnet for bad luck.
aku selalu dianggap pembawa sial, pembawa petaka.
But don't ever bring up my daughter in this conversation.
Tapi jangan pernah sekali pun membawa-bawa anakku.
We have decided.
Ini sudah menjadi keputusan kami.
You can't see how your family is paying for your ignorance.
Keluargamu yang kena imbasnya, kau tidak bisa melihatnya.
No, I can see it.
Aku lihat, Mbak.
But what do you know about my position?
Tapi apa Mbak pernah ada di posisiku
As a woman.
sebagai perempuan?
As a wife.
Punya suami,
As one who has carried her children in her womb.
mengandung,
As one who has given birth. Who has children.
melahirkan, punya anak.
You know nothing about that!
Tahu apa kalian?
- Sis! - How dare you?!
- Mbak! - Kurang ajar!
- Sis Ning. - You've crossed the line!
- Mbak Ning. - Keterlaluan kau!
- Enough. - You're evil!
- Mbak! - Biadab!
- That's unacceptable! - Calm down, Sis Ning.
- Keterlaluan kau! - Sudah, Mbak Ning.
- Calm down. - I know I brought a curse with me!
- Sudah. - Memang aku pembawa sial!
I brought bad luck to this family!
- Memang aku pembawa petaka! - Sudah, Din!
I married a bad match!
Setelah menikah dengan suami yang salah.
You're a coward, Banyu! You can't control your wife!
Kau ini laki-laki tidak punya harga diri! Tidak becus mengurus istri!
Calm down, sis. Calm down!
- Sabar, Mbak. - Sabar!
Let's do the cleansing ceremony tomorrow.
Besok kita ruwatan.
- Poor Rana. - Calm down, Din. Just let them.
Kasihan Rana, Mas.
Calm down.
Sabar.
Okay?
Ya?
No, honey.
Jangan, Mas.
- If Rana is still alive... - She is.
- Kalau Rana masih hidup... - Masih, Mas.
- Then there's nothing to be afraid of. - She's still alive.
- Kita tidak perlu takut lagi. - Masih hidup.
Aunt Nur.
Bude Sepuh,
Why are you so afraid of me?
mengapa takut sama Rana?
Tari.
Tari,
Where are you going?
mau ke mana?
To the woods.
Ke hutan.
What are you gonna do in the woods?
Mau apa?
They say when we do the cleansing ceremony,
Katanya kalau lagi ada ruwatan pembersihan diri,
we will find her body, Uncle.
jasadnya akan kembali, Pakde.
That's just hearsay.
Itu baru katanya. Semua tidak ada yang pasti.
What if your parents are looking for you?
Bagaimana jika bapak dan ibumu mencari?
They'll be too busy with the ceremony. Nobody will notice I'm not here.
Bapak dan Ibu sedang repot. Tidak ada yang sadar kalau Tari pergi.
I know.
Pakde tahu
You're feeling guilty, Janu.
kau merasa bersalah, Janu.
And you, Tari...
Dan kau, Tari,
You need to do something good.
kau ingin berbuat sesuatu.
But I think
Tapi menurut Pakde,
there's nothing for you to prove.
kalian berdua tidak perlu membuktikan apa-apa.
But this is for Rana.
Tapi ini buat Mbak Rana.
We're running out of time, Uncle.
Sudah tidak ada waktu lagi, Pakde.
Excuse me, Mr. Puppeteer.
Permisi, Pak Dalang.
I will let my daughter, Rana,
Aku pasrahkan
be cleansed.
supaya diruwat.
Thank you.
Baik.
I accept your request.
Aku terima permintaanmu.
Your daughter, Rana, will be cleansed
Putrimu, Rana, akan diruwat
the way it has to be done.
sebagaimana mestinya.
"Mr. Dalang Kanda Buwana."
"Bapak Dalang Kanda Buwana."
"Bathara Kala."
"Bathara Kala."
"Yes, I'm here, Mr. Dalang."
"Ya, aku di sini, Saudara Dalang."
"Where are you going?"
"Kau mau ke mana?"
"I'm looking for a girl who is the bearer of misfortune."
"Aku mau mencari seorang anak yang membawa nasib sial."
"Rana, the bearer of misfortune, has been offered to me."
"Rana, si pembawa nasib sial, itu sudah menjadi kurbanku."
"That is impossible." "Why is that?"
"Tidak bisa."
"I will purify her soul with Murwa Kala."
"Aku akan meruwatnya dengan cara Murwa Kala."
"If you think you can do it, do it right now!"
"Kalau kau bisa meruwatnya, lakukanlah sekarang juga!"
Honey?
Mbak...
Honey, this is Mommy.
Mbak, ini Ibu.
Rana, this is Mommy.
Rana, ini Ibu.
Wake up.
Sadar...
Sis, please help!
Mbak! Tolong, Mbak!
What is happening?
Mas, ini bagaimana?
Sis, enough. Have mercy on her.
Mbak, cukup. Kasihan, Mbak.
- Rana! - Sis... Mom. Sis.
Rana...
This is Mommy. Mommy...
Ini Ibu. Ibu di sini.
Janu?
Mas...
Janu.
Mas Janu?
Janu!
Mas Janu!
- Janu! - Tari?
- Mas Janu! - Tari?
Tari!
Tari!
- Janu! - Tari!
- Mas! - Tari!
Janu!
Mas!
Tari!
Tari!
Janu! Janu!
Mas! Mas Janu!
Honey.
Mbak!
Janu?
Mas?
Janu!
Mas!
Tari!
Tari!
Tari?
Tari?
Rana.
Mbak...
Rana is dead! Uncle! Banyu!
Rana meninggal! Pakde! Banyu!
Hey, sir!
Hei, Pak!
Sir! We found her!
Pak! Ketemu, Pak!
Sir! Ma'am!
Pak! Bu!
Mom, I was going to give this special gift to you.
Bu, tadinya Rana mau memberi kado spesial ini untuk Ibu.
But the weather today is bad.
Tapi ternyata cuacanya lagi tidak bagus.
Happy birthday, Mom.
Selamat ulang tahun ya, Bu.
I know you're the strongest person in the world.
Rana tahu Ibu adalah orang yang paling kuat.
That's why I also know, we're all going to be all right.
Itu sebabnya Rana juga tahu kalau kita semua akan baik-baik aja.
Because I have you.
Rana memiliki Ibu.
And you will always have me.
Dan Ibu juga selalu punya Rana.
Even when you are alone,
Kalau Ibu sendiri,
I know you're the strongest of them all.
Rana tahu Ibu adalah orang yang paling tangguh.
Don't ever listen to anyone who tells you that your birthday is on a cursed date.
Ibu tidak perlu mendengarkan kata orang
All the facts show we're all going to be fine, right, Mom?
Buktinya kita semua akan baik-baik saja, 'kan, Bu?
Happy birthday, Mom.
Selamat ulang tahun ya, Bu.
Please keep this video.
Disimpan videonya.
Because I want you to know
Supaya Ibu tahu
that I will always be with you.
Rana selalu ada di sebelah Ibu.
I will always be beside you.
Selalu menemani Ibu.
I wish you all the best, Mom.
Sehat-sehat ya, Bu.